{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "King Godfred built the Danevirke as a defense against this ruler, and later this ruler concluded the\nTreaty of Heiligen with the Hemming. This ruler, who died of pleurisy, was succeeded by his son Louis the\nPious, and three of his grandsons divided his empire in the Treaty of Verdun. This ruler, who was advised\nby Alcuin of York, was crowned on Christmas Day by Leo III as Imperator Romanorum. For ten points,\nname this King of the Franks who was the first Holy Roman Emperor.",
      "answer": [
        "Charlemagne",
        "Charles I",
        "Carolus Magnus"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "One member of this party gave the 7th of March speech, which cost him his Senate seat. Another\nmember of this party planned the American System. William Henry Harrison was the first of four\npresidents from this party, and Millard Fillmore was its last. For ten points, name this political party that\nrivaled the Democrats from the 1830’s to 1850’s before the formation of the Republican party.",
      "answer": [
        "Whig Party",
        "Whig"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This author wrote about a drunk Pope Julius II who tries to convince Julius into letting him into\nheaven in Julius Exclusus, and he advocated for Christians to act with faith in his Handbook of a Christian\nKnight. Hans Holbein created drawings for this man’s best known work, which satirizes the workings of\nthe Catholic Clergy. For ten points, name this Dutch humanist who wrote In Praise of Folly.",
      "answer": [
        "Desiderius Erasmus",
        "Erasmus"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "The documentary An Unreasonable Man examined this man, whose study of the Chevy Corvair led\nhim to advocate for seat belts and other basic safety features. He ran on a Presidential ticket with Winona\nLaDuke in a third party candidacy that some feel cost Al Gore the 2000 election. For ten points, name\nthis consumer activist and Green Party politician who wrote Unsafe at Any Speed.",
      "answer": [
        "Ralph Nader",
        "Nader"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This event was achieved by a man who purchased a .32 “Safety Automatic” Iver Johnson at the\nWalbridge hardware store and who was inspired by Gaetano Bresci’s murder of Umberto I of Italy. This\nevent, which occurred at the Temple of Music at the 1901 Pan American Exposition in Buffalo, was\ncarried out by Leon Czolgosz. For ten points, name this event, the killing of the 25th U.S. President.",
      "answer": [
        "Assassination of William McKinley",
        "Assassination of McKinley"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This composer wrote the twelve-tone Connotations for the opening of Lincoln Center. He quoted\n“Camptown Races” in a composition that features a narrator reciting the Gettysburg Address. He\ndepicted a couple in western Pennsylvania in a ballet choreographed by Martha Graham that incorporates\nthe Shaker hymn “Simple Gifts.” For ten points, name this American composer of Lincoln Portrait and\nAppalachian Spring.",
      "answer": [
        "Aaron Copland",
        "Copland"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Land acquired to create this city was bought from William Blaxton, and it built the first American\npublic school, its Latin School, in 1635. This capital of the Dominion of New England was the site of an\nincident on King Street involving snowballs and Redcoats that led to the death of Crispus Attacks. For\nten points, name this capital of Massachusetts, the site of a 1770 massacre.",
      "answer": "Boston"
    },
    {
      "question": "A war against the town of Visby led to a conflict between this country and the Hanseatic League.\nChristian I was the first member of this country’s Oldenburg dynasty, the oldest continuously reigning\ndynasty in Europe. This nation was briefly ascendant over Sweden and Norway in the Kalmar Union and\nis currently ruled by Frederik X. For ten points, name this country with capital at Copenhagen.",
      "answer": "Denmark"
    },
    {
      "question": "In one wartime film, this character wakes up from a dream where he had to work in a Nazi factory\ntightening shells. This star of Der Fuhrer’s Face has an uncle who is the richest character in their fictional\nuniverse .This character wears a sailor’s outfit with a red bow tie but no pants. This character’s nephews\nare Huey, Dewey, and Louie. For ten points, name this Disney-created duck.",
      "answer": [
        "Donald Duck",
        "Donald"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "One memorial to this policy is located on Eagle Harbor on Bainbridge Island. Those affected by it\nwere asked 28 questions; the last two were the “loyalty questionnaire.” Begun by Executive Order 9066,\nthis event was upheld by the Supreme Court in Korematsu v. U.S. For ten points, the United States\ncarried out what World War II-era process of deporting Asian-Americans to concentration camps?",
      "answer": [
        "Japanese internment",
        "Japanese-American internment"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "(TIEBREAKER BONUS QUESTION) In which World War II battle did Joe Rosenthal capture an image of Marines raising an\nAmerican flag?",
      "answer": [
        "Battle of Iwo Jima",
        "Iwo Jima"
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This kingdom defeated King Zwide [zwee-day] by dividing his army at the Mhlatuze [m-hlah-TOOzay] River. Mpande ruled this kingdom after surviving Dingane’s purges; Mpande’s son, Cetshwayo\n[keht-SHWAH-yoh], led this empire to an early victory at Isandlwana [ee-son-dull-WAH-nah] over the\nBritish before losing its capital, Ulundi, in 1879. For ten points, name this south African kingdom, led in\nthe early 19th century by Shaka.",
        "answer": [
          "Zulu",
          "Zulu Kingdom",
          "Zulu Empire"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Shaka developed the iklwa [ee-kull-wah], an improvement over the assegai, which was a thrown\nversion of this weapon. Greek hoplites carried a type of these called sarissae, which were often 20 feet long.",
        "answer": "spear"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "One holder of this position ordered the kidnapping of Adolf Eichmann. Another member of this\nposition said “I deeply regret that some perceive my being here as political,” in a 2015 address to Congress.\nThe only holder of this office to be assassinated was Yitzhak Rabin, and the only woman to hold this\nposition was Golda Meir. For ten points, name this position first held by David Ben-Gurion and currently\nheld by Benjamin Netanyahu, the head of state of a Middle Eastern Jewish country.",
        "answer": [
          "Prime Minister of Israel",
          "PM of Israel"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Netanyahu is a member of this Israeli political party, from which Ariel Sharon split to form the\nKadima party in 2005.",
        "answer": [
          "Likud Party",
          "Likud"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man noted that “The clock cannot be set back. You cannot restore Central Europe to 1870” in\na work that lamented Clemenceau’s “Carthaginian Peace.” This author of The Economic Consequences\nof the Peace argued that natural business cycles should be moderated by government intervention. For\nten points, name this British economist who outlined modern macroeconomics with his General Theory\nof Employment, Interest, and Money.",
        "answer": [
          "John Maynard Keynes",
          "Keynes"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This New York Times columnist and modern Keynesian thinker won the 2008 Economics Nobel\nPrize as his theories of international trade were being tested in the recovery from the Great Recession.",
        "answer": [
          "Paul Krugman",
          "Krugman"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Tomas Cloma established the Free Territory of Freedomland in this body of water. The “nine-dotted\nline” designates one country’s territorial claims in this body of water. Several countries dispute the\npotential oil reserves of this body of water’s Paracel and Spratly Islands. For ten points, name this body\nof water that borders the Philippines, Vietnam, and a large Asian country.",
        "answer": [
          "South China Sea",
          "South China"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This island, part of the smallest Chinese province, is in the South China Sea. China claims the\nSpratly Islands as part of this island province.",
        "answer": "Hainan"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Supposedly, prior to this battle, Cyrsillus and his wife were stoned for suggesting surrender. Washed\nup sailors were slaughtered on Psyttaleia [sit-uh-LYE-uh] by Aristides [air-uh-STY-dees], and a throne\nwas erected for the losing commander to watch the battle. This battle vindicated the “wooden walls”\nof Themistocles, who advocated abandoning Athens prior to this battle. The battles of Artemisium and\nThermopylae were fought prior to, for ten points, what naval battle, a victory for the allied Greeks over\nXerxes I?",
        "answer": [
          "Battle of Salamis",
          "Salamis"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "One commander under Xerxes was Queen Artemisia of this place, which was also the birthplace\nof Herodotus and the site of a notable mausoleum.",
        "answer": "Halicarnassus"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This year saw the National Liberal party push Frederick VII to create a new constitution, which made\nhim share power with the Rigsdag. This year saw William O’Brien lead the Young Irelander Rebellion,\nand the March Revolution in this year in Germany led to the Frankfurt Assembly offering the German\ncrown to Wilhelm IV. Klemens von Metternich resigned as Chancellor of Austria in this year, which\nsaw the establishment of the French Second Republic. For ten points, name this year that saw multiple\nrevolutions against various European Governments.",
        "answer": "1848"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Wilhelm IV was from this royal line that would rule Imperial Germany until the end of WW1.",
        "answer": [
          "Hohenzollern Dynasty",
          "Hohenzollern"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Participants in this event followed Tom the Tinker and were radicalized by the Mingo Creek\nAssociation. Albert Gallatin tried to prevent this event, in which Robert Johnson was tarred and feathered\nby a mob and John Neville’s house was ambushed during the Battle of Bower Hill. The Watermelon Army\ncommanded under Henry “Lighthorse” Harry Lee was sent to put down this rebellion under orders of\nPresident George Washington. For ten points, name this 1794 rebellion caused by an excise tax on an\nalcoholic drink.",
        "answer": [
          "Whiskey Rebellion",
          "Whiskey"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Whiskey Rebellion occurred in this state that also saw a massacre led by the Paxton Boys\nand Fries’ Rebellion.",
        "answer": "Pennsylvania"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This city was the capital of a sultanate that, after losing the Battle of Marj Dabiq, was conquered\nin 1517 by Selim I. Muhammad Ali Pasha westernized this former capital of the Mamluk sultanate and\ncurrent capital of the Arab League. Port Said [sai-EED] is north of, and the Suez Canal is east of, for ten\npoints, what city whose outskirts are home to the Great Pyramid of Giza, the capital of Egypt?",
        "answer": "Cairo"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Egypt was expelled from the Arab League after signing a separate peace treaty with this country,\nwhich it first recognized in that treaty.",
        "answer": "Israel"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "ITALIAN CITIES",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Is home to the Colosseum?",
          "answer": "Rome"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the supposed site of Galileo’s experiment dropping weights off the Leaning Tower?",
          "answer": "Pisa"
        },
        {
          "question": "Is situated on over one hundred islands, separated by canals?",
          "answer": "Venice"
        },
        {
          "question": "Is the capital of Tuscany and the birthplace of the Renaissance?",
          "answer": "Florence"
        },
        {
          "question": "Is home to La Scala Opera House and was ruled by the Visconti family?",
          "answer": "Milan"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the birthplace of Christopher Columbus?",
          "answer": "Genoa"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the “fair” setting of Shakespeare’s Romeo and Juliet?",
          "answer": "Verona"
        },
        {
          "question": "Is home to many of Palladio’s villas and an 800-year old university where Galileo taught math?",
          "answer": "Padua"
        }
      ],
      "prompt": "Which Italian city..."
    },
    {
      "category": "THE SOVIET UNION",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Its capital, which hosted the boycotted 1980 Summer Olympics?",
          "answer": "Moscow"
        },
        {
          "question": "the walled fortress near Red Square where Soviet leaders ruled?",
          "answer": "Kremlin"
        },
        {
          "question": "The dictator whose 1938 Great Purge ousted political dissidents?",
          "answer": [
            "Joseph Stalin",
            "Stalin",
            "Josef Vissarionovich Dzhugashvilli",
            "Dzhugashvilli"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Its intelligence agency, once led by Yuri Andropov?",
          "answer": [
            "KGB",
            "Komitet gosudarstvennoy bezopasnosti",
            "Committee for State Security"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "the Soviet defense treaty meant to counter NATO?",
          "answer": "Warsaw Pact"
        },
        {
          "question": "Its final Premier, who resigned in 1991?",
          "answer": [
            "Mikhail Gorbachev",
            "Gorbachev"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "the process of political restructuring that hastened the end of the USSR?",
          "answer": "perestroika"
        },
        {
          "question": "The agency led by Nikolai Yezhov which carried out the Great Purge?",
          "answer": [
            "NKVD",
            "Narodnyy Komissariat Vnutrennikh Del"
          ]
        }
      ],
      "prompt": "In this history of the Soviet Union, who or what was..."
    },
    {
      "category": "BILL CLINTON",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Is married to which Democratic Presidential candidate?",
          "answer": [
            "Hillary Rodham Clinton",
            "Hillary",
            "Hillary Clinton"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Served with which Vice President?",
          "answer": [
            "Al Gore",
            "Gore"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Served as the governor of what state?",
          "answer": "Arkansas"
        },
        {
          "question": "Had an “inappropriate relationship” with which White House intern?",
          "answer": [
            "Monica Lewinsky",
            "Lewinsky"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Earned what academic honor, allowing him to study in Oxford?",
          "answer": [
            "Rhodes scholarship",
            "Rhodes"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Signed what law that was later ruled unconstitutional by the Supreme Court in U.S. v. Windsor?",
          "answer": [
            "Defense of Marriage Act",
            "Defense of Marriage",
            "DOMA"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Issued over 100 of what orders on his last day in office, controversially including tax evader Marc\nRich?",
          "answer": "pardons"
        },
        {
          "question": "employed which first female Attorney General?",
          "answer": [
            "Janet Reno",
            "Reno"
          ]
        }
      ],
      "prompt": "Bill Clinton..."
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) After being defeated in World War I, this country lost much of its land in the Treaty of\nTrianon, but some of that land was later restored by Austria in the First Vienna Award.\nThe Nazi-backed (20 pts) ",
        "Arrow Cross Party ended this country’s “regency” after it overthrew\nMiklos (10 pts) ",
        "Horthy. In the aftermath of World War II, this country was occupied by the Soviet Union,\nwhich later put down this country’s 1956 Revolution. For ten points, name this European country with\ncapital Budapest."
      ],
      "answer": "Hungary"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) John Aaron rationed battery power during this event. Ken Mattingly was supposed to\nhave participated in this event but was unable due to (20 pts) ",
        "German Measles, while Fred\nHaise suffered a serious urinary tract infection during it. During this event, the service (10 pts) ",
        "module’s number 2 oxygen tank suffered a failure, causing Jack Swigert and Jim Lovell to report\n“Houston, we’ve had a problem”. For ten points, name this NASA mission whose moon landing was\naborted but which returned safely to Earth."
      ],
      "answer": "Apollo 13"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) One of these conflicts was triggered by the seizure of a ship believed to be held by\npirates, the Arrow. Lin Zexu served as a naval commander during the first of these wars\nthat was ended with the Treaty of the (20 pts) ",
        "Bogue. Another of these wars was started by\nthe Kowloon Incident. Their aftermath ended the (10 pts) ",
        "Canton System with the “unequal treaty”\nof Nanking. For ten points, name these 19th century wars fought in China over a drug processed from\npoppies."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Opium Wars",
        "Opium"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Alicia Garza and Patrisse Cullors are credited with originating this movement. In\nAugust 2015, Elizabeth Hasselbeck questioned whether this group should be identified as a (20 pts) ",
        "hate group, while other opposition to this movement has focused on support for law\nenforcement. Though it was created in (10 pts) ",
        "2013, it became nationally prominent after the death of\nMichael Brown. For ten points, name this civil rights protest movement whose three-word name protests\nthe lack of human rights for a minority group."
      ],
      "answer": "Black Lives Matter"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This painting is a companion to The Charge of the Mamelukes. It includes a cubic\nlantern that illuminates the pile of bodies below the group on the left. In this work, a (20 pts) ",
        "monk huddles near a man in white and yellow, who stands with his arms stretched upwards\nin (10 pts) ",
        "surrender. For ten points, name this painting in which a shadowy Napoleonic firing squad takes\naim at Spanish citizens in Madrid, a painting by Francisco Goya."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "The Third of May 1808: The Execution of the Defenders of Madrid",
        "The Third of May 1808",
        "El tres de mayo de 1808 en Madrid",
        "El tres de mayo de 1808",
        "Los fusilamientos de la montana del Principe Pio",
        "Los fusilamientos del tres de mayo"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) An incident in this body of water’s Macondo Prospect led to a moratorium announced\nby Ken Salazar. A delta known as the Bird’s Foot extends into this body of water, whose\ncoast is home to many (20 pts) ",
        "bayous. Oil gushed into this body of water for 87 days in 2010\nafter the Deepwater Horizon explosion, and a (10 pts) ",
        "2005 hurricane that gained strength here\ndevastated New Orleans. For ten points, name this gulf of the Atlantic Ocean where Hurricane Katrina\nstruck the Mississippi River Delta."
      ],
      "answer": "Gulf of Mexico"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This agreement resolved the underlying dispute of Cresap’s War. David Rittenhouse and\nAndrew Ellicott finished mapping this agreement after Iroquois guides refused to cross into (20 pts) ",
        "Lenape territory. It includes a 12-mile arc around New Castle, outside of which lies a\n“wedge” once claimed by both (10 pts) ",
        "Delaware and Pennsylvania. This agreement is named for the\ntwo British surveyors who mapped it. For ten points, name this line geographically separating Maryland\nand Pennsylvania, which symbolically separated free Northern states from slave-owning Southern states."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Mason-Dixon line",
        "Mason-Dixon"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) One battle at this site saw Bruno von Mudra and Karl von Eimen lead assaults on\nthe French Fourth army under Henri Gouraud. Another battle here was preceded by the\nreplacement of Charles (20 pts) ",
        "Lanzerac with Louis d’Esprey for “lacking offensive spirit.”\nAfter that battle, Helmuth (10 pts) ",
        "Von Moltke proclaimed “Majesty, we have lost the war” and\nabandoned the Schlieffen plan. Taxicabs brought soldiers to, for ten points, what site of an early Allied\nvictory in WW1 that saved Paris?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Marne River",
        "Marne",
        "Battles of the Marne River"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) (TIEBREAKER EXAMPLE QUESTION) Writing under the name “Hercules,” Jesse Hawley put forth an idea for this\nobject, which was laid out by James Geddes and Benjamin Wright. The “Bucktails”\nwere annoyed with Governor (20 pts) ",
        "DeWitt Clinton over this object, which connected\nthe Mohawk and Hudson rivers and ran from (10 pts) ",
        "Albany to Buffalo. For ten points, name\nthis canal built in New York during the early 19th century."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Erie Canal",
        "Erie"
      ]
    }
  ]
}